<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>George Morgan plaintife [brace] William Megges, Richard Bowdler, William Turner, Thomas Ihones, Sir Iohn Bourcher, William Essington, and Robert Barlow ... defendants</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18102A.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23891569</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23891569</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26954</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07717)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26954)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1837:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>George Morgan plaintife [brace] William Megges, Richard Bowdler, William Turner, Thomas Ihones, Sir Iohn Bourcher, William Essington, and Robert Barlow ... defendants</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Court of Chancery.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Concerns bankruptcy of Bowdler and Co. (or Allum Co.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Morgan, George.</term>
               <term>Bowdler and Co.</term>
               <term>Alum industry --  England.</term>
               <term>Business failures --  England.</term>
               <term>Actions and defenses --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26954:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>George Morgan</hi> plaintife, <hi>William Megges, Richard Bowdler, William Turnor, Thomas Ihones,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Bourcher, William Eſsington,</hi> and <hi>Robert Barlow,</hi> Defendants.</head>
            <head type="sub">And betwixt <hi>Richard Bowdler</hi> plaintife, and <hi>George Morgan</hi> defendant.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <label>1609. May 6.</label> 
                  <hi>Bowdler, Turnor, Ihones,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Bourcher,</hi> Farmed the Allum workes of his Maieſtie, and <hi>Eſſington,</hi> and <hi>Barlow,</hi> were partners with them therein.</p>
               <p>Theſe men wanting monyes to ſupply the workes, agreed that <hi>Bowdler,</hi> (who had formerly lyued at Myddelborow,) and had ſeruants, and Factors reſident there, ſhould be the Agent, to procure monyes there at intreſt, <hi>and by way of exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Megges,</hi> being Father in law, and Brother in law, to <hi>Bowdler,</hi> to giue ayde therevnto, lent <hi>Bowdler</hi> his name, and credit, withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lymitation, to take vp monyes, and ſubſcribe his name to bills of Exchange, whereby <hi>Megges,</hi> and <hi>Bowdler,</hi> became as one, And by this meanes all the defendants, were all, as one ioynt body, and knowne both in England, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne parts, by the name of the Allum Company, or of <hi>Bowdler</hi> and Company.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1609. Octob.</label> 
                  <hi>Bowdler</hi> and Company, made choyce of the plaintife <hi>Morgan</hi> to be their Factor at Myddelborow, in their imployment, and when euer <hi>Morgans</hi> credit would not ſerue, to procure monyes enough to pay their bills of Exchange, and ſupply their occaſions, he wrote to them of it, by dyrecting his letters, to <hi>Richard Bowdler</hi> and Company, and what euer hee wrote of therein to bee performed by <hi>Megges, Turnor,</hi> or any other of them, the ſame was from time, to time, performed, by them, as if the letters, had beene written to each of them in particular, <hi>Bowdler</hi> being authorized to receiue, and write letters, and to receiue and take <hi>Morgans</hi> accompts.</p>
               <p>To this end <hi>Megges, Turnor, Bowdler,</hi> and the reſt, weekely charged <hi>Morgan</hi> with great ſummes of mony by exchange: and to inable <hi>Morgans</hi> credit, to take vp monyes to pay thoſe bills, they ſent him ſeuerall vnlimited letters of credit, and procuration, ſome in one kinde, ſome in another, dyuers of them being regiſtred, both in England, and elſewhere, at Publike Notaryes vnder their hands, and ſeales, for any man to reade, and take coppies of that would (as very many did) thereby declaring to all men, that whoſoeuer truſted their Factor <hi>Morgan</hi> reſident in Myddelborow, they all thereby obliged themſelues, as principall debters for repayment thereof.</p>
               <p>This imployment of <hi>Morgans</hi> being onely to pay bils, and to take vp monyes by exchange wherewith to pay it, was ſuch as muſt (of <hi>Neceſſity)</hi> haue, and accordingly had, <hi>Weekely,</hi> Interchangeable letters and accompts, and euery 4. 5. or 6. moneths (or oftner if the ſame were required) <hi>Morgan</hi> ſent <hi>Bowdler</hi> and Company, a generall accompt, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all thoſe former weekely accompts.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1611. Febr. 5.</label> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> came into England, and accompted for all things (for which he had not formerly accompted) and then was made free of London by <hi>Bowdler,</hi> and receiued vp his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture of Apprentiſhip, and friends bonds; And <hi>Bowdler</hi> publikely acknowledged, <hi>Morgans</hi> faithfull ſeruice, which according to the cuſtome of London, is as a releaſe for all time paſt: And <hi>Morgan,</hi> by their perſwaſion, returned backe to Myddelborow, into his former imployment.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1612. May. 20.</label> This contynued from October 1609. vntill the 20. of May 1612. that all the partners (but <hi>Megges)</hi> fayled and became, inſoluent.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1612. May. 23.</label> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> delyuered to <hi>Bowdler</hi> and Company his laſt generall accompt, intitled, <hi>Bowdler or Allum Accompt,</hi> according to his bookes of accompt, and therein ſet downe the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of 37794. pounds, 4. ſhillings, and 7. pence, Flemiſh money, which is, 22600. pounds ſtarling, then owing by them by exchange, and intreſt, for the ſaid accompt, whereof 6251. pounds, 10. ſhillings, and 2. pence Flemiſh, which is, 3460. pounds ſtarling, was due to <hi>Morgan.</hi> And for the reſidue <hi>Morgan</hi> was then ingaged for them as their Factor.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1612. May. 29.</label> This accompt was axamined, and allowed of, and <hi>Bowdler</hi> ſealed <hi>Morgan A generall releaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>1612. May. 31.</label> All the defendants, but <hi>Megges,</hi> procured a protection from his Maieſty as ioynt copartners in the Allum buſines, and that being expired, after procured diuers others ſucceſſiuely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> demanding payment of <hi>Megges,</hi> he denied and forſwore his hand to all the bils of Exchange produced for aboue 40000. pound, alledging <hi>Bowdler</hi> had counterfetted the ſame, without his conſent, or authority, although ſince, <hi>Morgan</hi> hauing payd dyuers of thoſe bills, he hath confeſſed in his Anſwere to <hi>Morgans</hi> bill, that he gaue <hi>Bowdler</hi> leaue, and the rather then confeſſed (becauſe the bills were paid,) but vntill he had aſſurance that <hi>Morgan</hi> had payd them, he forſwore all.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1614.</label> The defendants, exhibited an accompt to the King as partners in the Allum buſineſſe, and thereby procured payment of 36100. pounds ſtarling, beſides 50000. pounds receiued for Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſold by them, whereof, 15000. pound was for intreſt, factoridge, and <hi>(loſſe by exchange)</hi> therein expreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1615. and 1616.</label> The defendants, ended with their creditors, and all of them appeared to the world (ſaue onely <hi>Bowdler)</hi> who ſtill abſented himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1616. Noue. 21.</label> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> vrging them to pay what was due vnto him, by his ſaid laſt accompt of 23. of May 1612. and to free him of the ſaid ingagements, <hi>Bowdler</hi> in ſtead of payment, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits his bill in Chancery to be relieued for 3000. pound, error in <hi>Morgans</hi> accompts, as he pretended in 1609. 1610. 1611. and 1612.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1617. Aprill. 7.</label> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> exhibits his bill againſt them all, (as one ioynt body,) to be relieued of thoſe debts, and ingagements, mentioned in the ſaid accompt of 23. of May 1612.</p>
               <p>The defendants, delay him by Trickes to Anſwere, ſome by demurrers, and ſome by imperfect Anſweres, and about December 1617. <hi>Bowdler</hi> and the reſt, petitioned to the Maſter of the Rolls, to haue the matter referred to fiue Merchants Aduenturers, to which <hi>Morgan</hi> conſented.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1617. Decem. 20.</label> An order and Commiſſion was directed to <hi>Robert Palmer,</hi> and foure other Merchants Aduenturers.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to take the defendants, <hi>Megges</hi> and <hi>Bowdlers</hi> Anſwers, to <hi>Morgans</hi> bill to all things wherevnto they had demurred.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to examine all parties and witneſſes, vpon oath, and to heare and determine, or certifie.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that they ſhould <hi>forbeare</hi> to meddle, concerning a bond of 900. which <hi>Morgan</hi> ſealed to <hi>Megges</hi> (as ſurety for <hi>Bowdler,)</hi> and for which hee had <hi>Bowdlers</hi> bond of 1000. pound to ſaue him harmeleſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1617. Decem. 30.</label> Six of the defendants, entred bonds to performe ſuch order of Court, as ſhould be made vpon their certificate, by vertue of the ſaid Commiſſion. <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Megges,</hi> in 4000. pounds.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Turnor,</hi> in 4000. pounds.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bowdler,</hi> in 5000. pounds.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ihones,</hi> in 2000. pounds.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eſſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>000. pounds.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Barlow,</hi> in 2000. pounds.</item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Bourcher</hi> promiſed to performe but refuſed to ſeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a bond as the others did.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>1618. Octo. 7.</label> This Commiſſion expired, and no end made, the Commiſſioners perſwaded <hi>Morgan</hi> to enter bond to ſtand to their <hi>Award,</hi> which he conſented to doe, <hi>Prouided, all the ſaid parties,</hi> would doe the like: wherevpon onely <hi>Megges, Bowdler,</hi> and <hi>Turnor,</hi> ſealed bonds to ſtand to their <hi>Award. But, Ihones, Eſſington, Barlow,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Bourcher,</hi> refuſing, (and <hi>Morgan</hi> diſliking the carriage of the ſaid Arbitrators.)</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1618. Octob. 15.</label> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> obtayned <hi>A new Commiſſion,</hi> wherein ſixe other graue Merchants were added to thoſe fiue Arbitrators, with the like directions as the <hi>former Commiſſion</hi> of the 20. of December. 1617.</p>
               <p>But they refuſed to proſeede as Commiſſioners, and <hi>Morgan</hi> being bound to performe their Award, and but onely three of the defendants.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1618. Ianua. 5.</label> They made an Award, and ordered <hi>Morgan</hi> to pay <hi>Bowdler</hi> 579. pounds, and ſixe ſhillings, Alſo <hi>Morgan</hi> to ceaſe all ſuits againſt, <hi>Megges, Ihones, Eſſington, Barlow,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> becauſe (they ſay) they neither ought to pay, or performe, any thing to <hi>Morgan,</hi> yet neither <hi>Ihones, Eſſington, Barlow,</hi> or Sir <hi>Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>her,</hi> did euer ſubmit themſelues to ſtand to their Award: With diuers other things, not referred to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1618. Ianua. 21.</label> Vpon motion in Court, his Lordſhip ordred that the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>formance of the ſaid Award ſhould be ſpared, and the cauſe to proceed to examination of witneſſes, and ſo iudicially in ordinary courſe, and that for theſe 11. cauſes (amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t diuers other reaſons,) heereafter following. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, They neuer tooke the Anſwers of <hi>Megges,</hi> and <hi>Bowdler,</hi> vnto <hi>Morgans</hi> bill, wherevnto they had demurred, which was the firſt thing directed them in their Commiſſion to be performed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They did neuer examine any parties or witneſſes, during all their proceedings, but onely <hi>Iohn Grenowes,</hi> who is Couſin German to <hi>Bowdler,</hi> (a man deepely ingaged for <hi>Bowdler.)</hi> And being at the ſame time <hi>Bowdlers</hi> Factor in other imployment, and chargeable for thoſe monyes himſelfe, ſweares to free himſelfe by cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ging <hi>Morgan</hi> therewith.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, For that but three of the ſeuen defendants did, or would ſubmit themſelues, or ſeale bonds, to ſtand to their Award, yet they charged <hi>Morgan</hi> for all ſeuen of them, and Awarded <hi>Morgan</hi> to ceaſe all ſuits againſt them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, For that they charged <hi>Morgan</hi> not onely for the 4. defendants, (who neuer entred bonds to performe their Award,) but alſo for 3. others, <hi>viz. Pasfield, Grenowes,</hi> and <hi>Aynſcombe, Bowdlers</hi> Factors, who were all meere ſtrangers, both to the ſute, and alſo to their Award, or Arbiterment.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, They allowed <hi>Bowdler</hi> diuers great ſummes which they pretended <hi>Morgan</hi> receiued for <hi>Bowdler</hi> in 1607. and 1608. which is before the time that <hi>Bowdler</hi> demands reliefe by his owne bill, for his bill is but for pretended errors in 1609. 1610. 1611. and 1612.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, They Awarded <hi>Morgan</hi> to allow <hi>Bowdler</hi> great ſummes, which <hi>Bowdler</hi> neuer demanded of him, by his bill, or otherwayes, and for which <hi>Morgan</hi> neuer heard of vntill after their Award, whereby he could giue no Anſwere to them.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, They allow <hi>Bowdler</hi> aboue. 8000. pounds more then euer he demanded in his bill, for his bill is but for 3000. pounds, and they allow him aboue 11000. pounds ſtarling.</p>
               <p>Eightly, They awarded <hi>Bowdler, Turnor,</hi> and Company, to free <hi>Morgan</hi> from Maſter <hi>Peter Courten</hi> and aboue 40. other of their creditors in all, for aboue 18000. ſtarling, yet they neuer mention who that company was: And for thoſe that truely were that company, namely, <hi>Megges, Ihones, Eſſington, Barlow,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Bourcher,</hi> although none of them but <hi>Megges</hi> euer entred bonds to <hi>Morgan</hi> to ſtand to their Award, (or <hi>Morgan</hi> to them) yet they Awarded <hi>Morgan</hi> to ceaſe all ſuit againſt euery one of them by name, and ordred that none of them ought to pay or performe any thing to <hi>Morgan.)</hi> Yet they neuer ordred that all they, or any of them ſhould ceaſe all ſuits againſt <hi>Morgan,</hi> neither did they declare that <hi>Morgan</hi> neither ought to pay or performe any thing to them.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, And for that bond of 900. pound, which <hi>Morgan</hi> ſealed to <hi>Megges,</hi> for <hi>Bowdlers</hi> debt, which bond did ariſe, by reaſon <hi>Megges</hi> pretended his bills of exchange to be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetted by <hi>Bowdler,</hi> (with which bond they were in their Commiſſion expreſſely forbidden to meddle,) Neuertheleſſe, they awarded <hi>Morgan</hi> to ſeale releaſes to <hi>Megges,</hi> and <hi>Bowdler,</hi> and thereby <hi>Morgan</hi> ſhould diſcharge <hi>Bowdlers</hi> counterbond of 1000. pound, to ſaue him harmeleſſe from that bond of 900. pound, (without giuing <hi>Morgan</hi> any allowance for it.) Yet they neuer Awarded <hi>Megges</hi> either to ſeale <hi>Morgan</hi> a releaſe, or to deliuer him vp the ſaid bond of 900. pound. By which meanes <hi>Morgan</hi> ſhould acquit his counterbond for nothing, and yet be left lyable to pay <hi>Megges</hi> the 900. pound for <hi>Bowdlers</hi> debt.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, They Awarded <hi>Morgan</hi> to pay the 579. pounds, 6. ſhillings, within three monthes, yet they limit <hi>Bowdler, Turnor,</hi> and Company no time to free <hi>Morgan</hi> from Maſter <hi>Peter Courten,</hi> and the other Creditors, which is for aboue, 18000. pound ſtarling ingagements, ſo as <hi>Morgan</hi> ſhould firſt pay his ready money to <hi>Bowdler,</hi> and then hee ſhould be the leſſe able to proſecute lawe againſt them for his owne money, and to be freed of the ſayd ingagements, a great part of which ingagements, <hi>Morgan</hi> hath ſince beene inforced to pay for them.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, They neuer purſued the directions of their Commiſſion in any one particular, but proceeded moſt erroniouſly, in diuers other things as well as theſe, (but all they did, was ſtill to <hi>Morgans</hi> preiudice.)</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1618. Ianua. 28.</label> Vpon hearing counſell at large on both ſides the ſayd order of 21. Ianuary was confirmed for the 11. cauſes aforeſaid, and it was ordred that the ſaid Arbitrators ſhould rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer <hi>Morgan</hi> all the bonds, bills of exchange, and letters, deliuerd into their hands by him, whereby to make his proofes in Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1618. Febr. 6.</label> The fiue Arbitrators wrote to the Lord Chauncellor, and went in perſon to him. And petitioned to him, that they might not certifie the particulars of their Award, and vſed all meanes they could that their owne Award might ſtand in force.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1618. Febr. 19.</label> and 22. It was againe orderd they ſhould redeliuer backe all <hi>Morgans</hi> bonds, bills of exchange, letters, and other writings (which they receyued of him,) yet the Arbitrators would not obey any of theſe orders.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1618. Febr. 25.</label> 
                  <hi>Bowdler</hi> informed by petition, that all thoſe bonds and bils ſo demanded, were either counterfeted or ſatisfied, by making them payd in Accompt, And <hi>Bowdler</hi> procured it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to Sir <hi>Robert Rich</hi> Knight, one of the Maſters of the Chauncery, whether the ſame ought to be redeliuered to <hi>Morgan</hi> or not.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26954:2"/>
               <p>1618. March. 16. All the Arbitrators came home to him, and after hearing of all parties, and their councell, on both ſides, he certifieth, none were counterfeit, or ſatisfied, (as <hi>Bowdler</hi> alledged,) and therefore they ought to be redelyuerd backe to <hi>Morgan</hi> (according to diuers former orders) whereby to make his proofes in Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1619. Aprill. 15.</label> and Iune. 16. It was againe ordered they ſhould certifie the particulars of their Award, which they ſtill refuſed vntill <hi>Morgan</hi> forced them by an attachment, the 20. Iuly. 1619.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1619. Aug. 5.</label> They certified the particulars of their Award, which was in a certificate of 140. ſheetes of paper, wherein they allow <hi>Bowdler</hi> aboue 8000. pounds more then euer he demanded in his owne bill, beſides diuers other ſtrange errors, according as are heerein formerly expreſſed: And the better to credit, and countenance the ſame, they certifie, Maſter <hi>William Towerſon</hi> and Maſter <hi>Ralph Freeman,</hi> were priuy to all their ſaid proceedings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>SInce which time, <hi>Megges, Bowdler,</hi> and <hi>Turnor,</hi> haue anſwered vnto what before they had demurred, aboue 60. witneſſes haue beene examined in Court, after publication, and many hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and after certificates of Maſters of the Court, that the defendants owed to <hi>Morgan,</hi> and others 37794. pounds, 4. ſhillings and 7. pence Flemiſh, which is, 22600. pounds ſtarling according to <hi>Morgans</hi> ſayd laſt accompt, ending the 23. of May 1612. for which he ſtood ingaged for the ſaid Allum buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1619. Decem. 18.</label> His Lordſhip ſpent the whole day, both forenoone, and afternoone, in hearing the ſaid Award and certificates, and of all proceedings in the cauſe, And after to ſatisfie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and the world, as his Lordſhip then declared, (although God knowes he little ſatisfied <hi>Morgan</hi> thereby.) In ſtead of pronouncing iudgement, and a finall decree, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip nominated for new Commiſſioners, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <head>2. Maſters of the Chancery.</head>
                     <item>Sir <hi>William Birde,</hi> Knight.</item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Robert Rich,</hi> Knight.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>2. Aldermen of London.</head>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Middelton,</hi> Knight,</item>
                     <item>Maſter <hi>Robert Iohnſon,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>2. Merchants of London.</head>
                     <item>Maſter <hi>William Towerſon,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Maſter <hi>Ralph Freeman,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Which 2. Merchants the ſaid Arbitrators had certified were priuy to all their proceedings in making their ſaid Award.</p>
               <p>Theſe 6. Commiſſioners aſſiſted with the Auditors of the Chancery, were to examine all the ſaid Arbitrators Award, and the reaſons thereof, as alſo all accompts, letters, and all procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings from the beginning.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1619. March. 13.</label> After aboue 30. m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tings by them, and three monthes ſpent in preſence of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and their councell, And after their often conference with the ſaid Arbitrators, They all 7. ioyntly certified, that the defendants did owe to their Factor <hi>Morgan,</hi> and others to whom he ſtood ingaged for them by his laſt accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nding the 23. of May 1612. the ſaid 37794. pounds, 4. ſhillings, 7. pence Flemiſh, which is, 22600. ſtarling, according as had beene formerly certified, whereof,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> 3100. pounds ſtarling, was due to <hi>Morgan</hi> by foot of his ſaid laſt account.</p>
               <p>4386. pounds, 1. ſhilling, and 10. pence, ſtarling more which <hi>Morgan</hi> had ſince beene inforced to pay of the ſaid ingagements.</p>
               <p>14900. pounds ſtarling more, remaining yet vnſatisfied to Maſter <hi>Peter Courten</hi> and others all, which makes the ſaid 37794. pounds, 4. ſhillings, and 7. pence Flemiſh, or 22600. ſtarling, aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1620. May. 6.</label> This being heard againe all the forenoone, in open Court, in preſence of all parties, and their Councell, as alſo at other times, neither <hi>Party,</hi> nor <hi>Councell,</hi> denied the truth of the ſaid certificate, (as by the order appeares) but becauſe they indeuored to ſhift from being lyable to the ſaid decree, Therefore they obtained an order that they might make <hi>(new proofes,)</hi> by vertue whereof they haue after all the ſaid hearings, examined many witneſſes by way of <hi>ſupplimentall proofe,</hi> as alſo they haue examined <hi>Morgan</hi> himſelfe vpon many interrogatories.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1620. Iune, 19. and 26.</label> After all which the cauſe being againe heard in open Court, in preſence of all parties and their councell it was finally decreed, that <hi>Megges, Bowdler,</hi> and <hi>Ihones,</hi> ſhould pay <hi>Morgan</hi> 7486. pounds, 1. ſhilling, 10. pence ſtarling principall debt, due the 23. May 1612. for the generall Allum Accompt, and all intreſt and damage, as yet reſpited by his Lordſhip. Alſo <hi>Morgan</hi> is to be freed by them for 14900. pounds ſtarling ingagement for them. And it's not yet fully ended, whether the other foure, namely <hi>Turnor,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Burcher, Eſſington,</hi> and <hi>Barlow,</hi> ſhall be lyable to the ſaid decree or not.</p>
               <p>Which decree is accordingly 9. monthes ſince ſealed and inrowled, yet no part thereof performed, <hi>Megges</hi> not being to be found, <hi>Ihones</hi> ſubmitted himſelfe to the priſon of the Fleet, <hi>Bowdler</hi> appeares vnder protection of a Parliament man, and paies no man, hee ſtands out-lawed, and euer ſince May 1612. hee liued either vnder protection, or in obſcurity, and hath conuaied a great eſtate in truſt into the hands of <hi>Megges,</hi> his Father in law, the Lady <hi>Cambell</hi> his Mother and diuers others.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1620. Decem. 5.</label> All proces of Court as well ordinary as extraordinary being ſpent, againſt the ſaid <hi>Megges,</hi> and <hi>Bowdler,</hi> according to the ordinary courſe of the Court, his Lordſhip after all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vſuall courſe of the Court, <hi>Fined</hi> them two at 1000. pound a man for their many ſeuerall contempts, and not yeelding obedience to the ſaid decree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="1">1. FOr as much as the ſaid <hi>Megges,</hi> partners, and farmors, were all one ioynt body in the ſaid Allum buſineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For that all but <hi>Megges</hi> had ſeuerall protections from his Maieſty as one ioynt company:</p>
               <p n="3">3. For that all of them exhibited an accompt to his Maieſty as one body, and thereby receiued of his Maieſty 36100. pounds ſtarling, accordingly.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For that the petitioner <hi>Morgans</hi> ingagem ents did ariſe onely by being Factor for them all, for that Allum buſineſſe, as for one ioynt body.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For that all the petitioners demands appeare to be due by bills of exchange in writing, either vnderwritten, or accepted, by the ſaid partners.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And for that the truth of the petitioners cauſe not onely appeares, by a ioynt report made by 2. Maſters of the Chancery, 2. Aldermen of London, 2. Merchants of London, aſſiſted with the Auditors of the Chancery:</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Nota.</label> As alſo vpon many other ſeuerall Reports, all grounded vpon depoſitions, accompts, and writings proued in Court, and after 6. deliberate hearings in open Court, after that they had <hi>Supplimentall proofe,</hi> and examined the <hi>Petitioner vpon in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rrogatories.</hi> And the ſame finally <hi>Decreed</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Lord Chancellor:</p>
               <p>THe moſt humble petition of <hi>Morgan</hi> is, that the ſaid decree may be eſtabliſhed, and confirmed by act of Parliament, and as the ſaid partners were all one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to receiue of his Maieſty and others, and to engage the petitioner, ſo they may be as one ioynt body to ſatisfie him, and that all their lands and goods, which they are or ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eafter poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of, may be made all liable therevnto.</p>
               <p>And although they haue made fraudulent conueyances of their eſtates, yet if the ſame be hereafter diſcouered, that then all ſuch conueyances be made voyde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objections_and_answers">
               <p>
                  <hi>Here followeth</hi> Bowdler <hi>and Company, their Obiections to the decree, and</hi> Morgans <hi>anſwere therevnto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiection.</label> 
                  <hi>Bowdler</hi> did forbeare to examine witneſſes becauſe he relied vpon the Award, and certificate of the Arbitratorsand thereby he pretends to be preiudiced.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label> From Nouember. 1616. that <hi>Bowdler,</hi> exhibited his bill, vnto the 5. Ianuary, 1618. that the Award was made, which is 2. yeeres and a quarter he neuer examined any man, onely <hi>Iohn Grenowes,</hi> his Couſin German, and after the Award was ſuſpended, and directions by the Court, to proceed to examination of witneſſes, and ſo to a iudiciall hearing, in ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe, which was in Ianuary 1618. vntill the 1. of Nouember 1619. that publication was granted, he examined not one witneſſe: but then <hi>Bowdler</hi> vpon his owne petition brought his owne cauſe to hearing, which was in all 3. yeeres and a moneth. In all which time he might haue examined witneſſes if he would, if he had had any to examine, <hi>(as hee had not)</hi> onely he maketh that a colour for his bad dealing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiection.</label> That all the depoſitions taken by the Arbitrators, <hi>Robert Palmor</hi> and the reſt, were ſuppreſt, and not read before the 6. Commiſſioners, namely, 2. Maſters, 2. Aldermen, 2. Merchants.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label> They had no depoſitions (but onely <hi>Iohn Grenowes)</hi> to reade for <hi>Bowdler;</hi> and his depoſitions were often read and diſproued by 2. 3. or 4. other witneſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiection.</label> By the order of Reference dated 18. Decemb. 1619. it appeares, <hi>Bowdler</hi> deſired <hi>Morgan</hi> might be bound by any Account <hi>Bowdler</hi> could produce, if the ſame were vnder <hi>Morgans S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ruants</hi> hand: which was granted, but with this <hi>Prouiſo:</hi> That the ſaid Account ſo to be produced, muſt bee an Account formerly allowed of by <hi>Morgan,</hi> to bee his owne account, or elſe to be proued by 2. witneſſes that it was ſo allowed of by him, which witneſſes ſhould be neither Arbitrators, nor parties: and becauſe hee pretends none elſe were preſent, therefore it was impoſſible, as he ſaith, that he ſhould make any ſuch proofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> neuer did, or will deny any Account, or letter vnder his owne hand, but he will not be bound by any thing vnder any mans hand that hath been his <hi>Seruant; except</hi> the ſaid Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, or letters, were written or made by <hi>Morgan</hi> himſelfe, or by his conſent, <hi>Becauſe Bowdler</hi> and Company failed in May 1612. and <hi>Morgan then accounted</hi> with them, and alwayes wrote out his Accounts and letters himſelfe; <hi>and ſince Morgan</hi> hath had no dealings with him, nor giuen him, or any of them any Account. Beſides, ſince that time <hi>Morgan</hi> had a <hi>Seruant,</hi> namely, <hi>Iohn Quarles,</hi> who is <hi>Bowdlers</hi> Couſin German, (whom <hi>Bowdler</hi> inticed out of <hi>Morgans</hi> ſeruice) if he ſhould goe frame new falſe Accounts, and <hi>Bowdler</hi> ſay they were <hi>Morgans</hi> Accounts, ſo any man might bee defeated of all: And <hi>therefore</hi> that <hi>prouiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was iuſtly made in that order.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiection.</label> 
                  <hi>Bowdler</hi> alleageth, the Arbitrators certifie, <hi>Morgan</hi> confeſſed and yeelded to diuers parcels before them; which now he denies to allow vnto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> denyes any ſuch confeſſion: but if he had yeelded to ſome ſmall matters whereby to haue an end of ſuch great troubles; yet now hauing no end, but more trouble, he hath no reaſon to yeeld to more loſſe then needs muſt: Beſides, <hi>all which they</hi> certifie <hi>Morgan</hi> did confeſſe or yeeld vnto, amounts not vnto 400. pounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiection.</label> By the decree, the whole debt is laid but vpon 3. of the defendants, which ought to haue been vpon all ſeuen of them, and ſo the eaſier paid.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label> 
                  <hi>Morgan</hi> ſaith, all 7. ought to be lyable to pay him; and ſo deſireth that they may, and then they may enterpleade amongſt themſelues, how to diuide the payment thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>SO as if all <hi>Bowdler</hi> and Company their Allegations were true (as they are moſt falſe)</p>
               <p>Firſt, all which <hi>Iohn Grenowes</hi> depoſeth vnto, amounteth not vnto 1480. pounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Nota.</label> Secondly, all the pretended confeſſions of <hi>Morgan,</hi> amount not vnto 375. pounds. Both which is but 1855. pounds. And <hi>Bowdler</hi> by his owne bill demands but 3000. pounds. whereof this 1855. pound is part.</p>
               <p>Yet vnder colour of theſe falſe pretences of errour, although all amounts vnto but 1855. pounds ſtarling, <hi>Morgan</hi> hath thereby aboue 8000. pounds ſtarling, principall debt, detained from him, due 9. yeeres paſt, beſides all Intereſt, and damage for the ſame, which is in all proued to be abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 21000. pound ſtarling, beſides his Ingagements for them to Maſter <hi>Peter Courten,</hi> and others, amounting vnto 14900. pounds ſtarling more.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
